Hello Sunim
I'd like to learn about reincarnation
and previous lives.
I have some doubts about them.
The words we use,
the theories and ideologies
that we know were not formed recently.
Some were formed 2000 years ago,
others even 3000 years ago.
There are theories and ideologies
formed long ago
that have lasted throughout time.
But then there are many others
that have been discredited,
now that we know better.
In the old days, how did people interpret
violent waves during a sea storm?
They thought of it
as the wrath of the sea god.
They didn't know any other cause for it.
So they attempted
to calm the sea god's anger.
(Please don't bring more questions.
We'll be discussing this for a while.)
So they presented offerings
to the sea god
as a way to resolve the issue.
Should we say that those
people were foolish?
They were making the wisest decisions
they could during their time.
Did the common people
make such decisions?
Or was it the intellectuals that did?
It was the intellectuals of the time that
advised others to make such decisions.
Did they not also perform rituals
for solar and lunar eclipses?
They interpreted solar eclipses as
god's disapproval of the king's decisions.
There are many stories like these.
But now we all know
this isn't how things work.
We still have eclipses, do we not?
We still have sea storms, do we not?
These phenomenons still happen,
but we have uncovered their real causes.
So now we make ships bigger
so that they are tolerant to high seas.
We study the wind and wave patterns
to prevent damages
and alert people in advance.
We can't stop big waves from happening,
but we now predict and prepare for them.
We research and correspond to the issues.
And yet when it comes to religions,
we still follow illogical beliefs
from 2-3000 years back.
They were beliefs
of people who didn't know better,
and yet we still believe them.
In ancient times, religious groups
were the wisest group among the society.
But now religious groups have become
the most foolish ones.
Is to be elected president a choice of
the people or the choice of god?
If a choice of god, why are
elections even necessary?
The fact that we vote proves
it's the people's choice.
So should presidential
candidates pray to God?
Or should they focus on communicating
their vision across to voters?
And yet don't politicians pray
and seek fortune tellers
to find out whether they'll be elected?
As you see, we are subscribing
to beliefs from both the past and present.
On one hand, political
candidates campaign
and shake hands of people
asking for a vote.
On the other hand, they
pray to god to be elected.
It's all mixed up.
Hence the misunderstandings
come into play.
The concept of reincarnation was an
ideology formed five thousand years ago
by a native Indian tribe
known as the Dravidians.
When Aryans invaded and dominated India,
most of the Dravidian ideologies
were eradicated
while some were absorbed
into Brahman ideology.
This is how the concept of reincarnation
remains with us nowadays.
Rome conquered Israel, but
Christianity took over Rome, did it not?
Buddhism arose out of the reaction
against the illogicality of Brahmanism.
That's why in early Buddhist
teachings of the Shakyamuni Buddha,
there is no mentioning of reincarnation.
There are three types of
foolish beliefs in the world.
It is fatalism, unconditional belief in
reincarnation, and dependence on God.
Buddhism began in India
and remained throughout history,
hence it influenced the Indian society.
But traditional folk beliefs of India
also influenced Buddhist principles
the other way around.
That's why there are differences between
original teachings of Buddha
and later teachings of Indian Buddhism.
Do you understand?
Original Buddhism and Korean Buddhism
are also slightly different, is it not?
Original Buddhism didn't have shrines for
the Mountain Spirit or the Seven Stars.
But Koreans believed in the
Mountain Spirit and the Seven Stars,
hence such beliefs were
absorbed into Buddhism.
There were no such things as shrines
in the original teachings of the Buddha.
But over time, Indian Buddhism
absorbed folk beliefs of India.
Just as Koreans absorbed the Mountain
Spirit and Seven Stars into Buddhism,
Indians incorporated
their beliefs in Brahman,
Indra and all kinds of gods.
Hence the godly figures were created.
Such figures didn't exist
in early Buddhism.
During the transition
from early Buddhism to Mahayana,
lay Buddhists became the core
of Buddhism, instead of the monks.
The laymen living
in the secular world brought
in their native folk beliefs
into Buddhism.
And through Buddhism, traditional
Indian belief in reincarnation
was introduced to China.
To Chinese people, the ideology of
reincarnation came in with Buddhism.
Hence they thought reincarnation
was part of the Buddhist principles.
It's the same as how Koreans
think cilantro is a monk's vegetable
because monks brought it into Korea
And yet in India and China,
cilantro is a common vegetable
just like leek and lettuce.
Only because it was introduced
by monks in Korea,
we consider it a Buddhist food.
The way culture gets introduced
influences people's perceptions.
Reincarnation stems
from a folk belief from India.
It isn't a core belief of Buddhism.
You need to be able
to distinguish the two.
(Questioner) Then how did the principle
of interconnectedness originate?
One day, Buddha was on his way back
from seeking alms in the Buddha Grove.
He met a young man named
Sigala, who'd prostrated
once to the east, once to the south,
to the west and north.
The man repeated
prostrating in all directions.
Buddha asked him,
"Why are you prostrating to the east?"
The man said, "I don't know."
Buddha asked,
"Why are you prostrating to the west?"
"And to the south? To the north?"
And he replied, "I don't know."
Buddha then asked,
"Why are you even prostrating?"
The man replied, "My father told me to.
He said it's good for me
to prostrate towards the six directions."
So Buddha gave meaning behind prostrating
in six directions to the young man.
A wife's respect for her husband.
A husband's respect for his wife.
Parent's respect for children.
Children's respect for parents.
Teachers' respect for students.
Students' respect for teachers.
Those were the meanings
behind the six directions.
As I shared earlier on,
Buddha would at times declare
certain things as unnecessary.
For example, people believed
that bathing in the Ganges river
would wash away their sins.
When Buddha was asked if that was true,
he said, "If bathing in the Ganges
washes away all sins,
then all the fish in that river
would go to heaven."
He directly pointed out foolish beliefs.
In this case he could have told the man,
"Why are you wasting your time
prostrating without reason?" Instead,
he was compassionate
and avoided using
sharp words to criticize.
He gave meaning behind each direction :
A wife's respect for the husband
A husband's respect for the wife
Children's respect for parents
Parent's respect for children
Student's respect for the teacher
Teacher's respect for the student
This we now call the Sigala Sutra.
Then should we focus on the belief
that East represents
a husband's respect for the wife?
We shouldn't. Prostrating towards
the east isn't the important thing here.
What's important is how a husband
should be respecting his wife.
Buddha didn't stop the prostrations,
he simply gave context to the actions.
Regarding reincarnation, there are times
when the Buddha didn't comment at all.
Other times, he gave context to it that
is different from Indian traditions.
The same term would be used,
but with different meaning.
In such way he
explained interconnectedness.
Karma can also be explained this way.
"Do not try to avoid your karma."
This means that when you gladly accept
the karmic consequence of your actions,
you will no longer suffer.
If you don't want to face certain karmic
consequences, do not make certain choices.
"Do not make certain choices."
These are precepts.
"Accept karma willingly."
This is repentance.
Buddha guided us to the path
of enlightenment this way.
Now when I speak of Dharma like this,
is it easy or difficult to understand?
It's easier. But for older people,
it's still extremely
difficult for them understand.
So how do we make this easy for them?
We make it interesting
by adding a lot of examples.
As people are tied to their own thoughts
and find it hard to understand,
we blend old folk tales
into the Dharma.
Then it makes it an interesting story.
Buddha often infused the Dharma
into traditional fables,
proverbs and legends,
so the wider public could
easily understand it.
And it is such stories that
have been passed down to us.
Do you understand?
Buddha's teachings incorporate
ancient Indian fables,
and they now exist
under the name of Buddhism.
It is up to us to decide whether
we should insist these are
indeed Buddhist ideologies,
or only follow the fundamental teachings
of Buddha's path to enlightenment.
I'm saying that Buddhist scriptures
contain both Buddhist principles
and ancient fables.
I'd advise you to study
the fundamental teachings of Buddha
rather than study things
that were added out of
necessity throughout history.
Why? It is because you have
already studied a certain amount.
You already understand the Dharma as is.
I'll give you another example.
Have you even seen a shaman
performing a ritual?
Have you? Have you not too closely?
In the old days, when something
in a village gets stolen,
people brought in a shaman
to find the thief.
During the ritual, the shaman would pass
around a divine stick made of bamboo
and make each villager hold it.
The stick would start to shake.
The shaman would walk
around with the shaking stick
and stop in front of the thief's house.
That's how they'd catch thieves back then.
It's a similar approach to
a lie detector we have these days.
Back then, people would
know the phenomenon
but couldn't understand
the logic behind it.
So they called it divine revelation.
Today, we understand this as
a manifestation of the subconscious.
It relates to
how the subconscious reacts
when you're lying
vs when you're being honest.
Psychologically speaking,
when the shaman enters a trance,
she's actually accessing the subconscious.
Hence we call her a medium.
During a ritual, the shaman would
become a deceased family member.
She'd come out and start yelling,
"You bitch!"
Her voice and facial expressions
would be the same as the deceased person.
In the past we'd say
the soul of the deceased
entered the shaman as a medium.
Nowadays it's interpreted differently.
You'd know if you've studied psychology.
The shaman doesn't know
the deceased woman, does she?
But the daughter
of the deceased woman
has all the information
in her subconscious.
Each cell in our body has all the
information about our entire body.
And within each person,
the full history of mankind exists.
This woman's brain holds
the record of her parents,
and records of her grandparents
through her parent's memory.
It's like an archival
storage of a computer.
Within her subconscious,
knowledge of five previous
generations survives.
So we can understand that
when a shaman enters a trance,
she enters into the area
of the subconscious.
Just like transferring a file
from one computer to a disc,
the shaman accesses
the subconscious of other people.
Like telepathy, do you understand?
That's how she can perform
those things during trance.
For the same actions, the explanation
differs between the past and present.
What traditional beliefs used to consider
a mystery is now explained
through science.
And yet they are really the same thing.
In the past, things were only explained
in more abstract form
due to lack of knowledge.
Which became the basis for other stories.
This is why the time during
pregnancy is so important.
Your mindset during your pregnancy forms
the basis of the baby's foundation.
The first three years after birth define
the personality and
conscience of the baby.
Hence your mind and emotions
during pregnancy,
your feelings towards your husband form
the basis of your child's nature.
Many people ask me about how to deal
with their disobedient children.
To that I suggest they repent
to their in-laws and their husbands,
specifically because of this.
In the old days, people didn't understand
this. So how did they explain it?
They explained it by relying
on the concept of previous lives.
It's not entirely wrong.
But times have changed.
We can't spend too much time
exploring this topic today,
you'll learn more about it later.
Previous lives and reincarnation widely
represent Buddhism as a religion.
They are the things people first think of
when they think of Buddhism as religion.
But from the perspective of
the Dharma, the Buddhist principles,
Reincarnation and previous lives are not
core beliefs of Buddhism as a philosophy.
They are remnants of ancient Indian
culture that were infused into Buddhism.
(Questioner) But according to the Dharma,
(Questioner) everything is
interconnected through karma, is it not?
The principle of interconnectedness can
be seen from many different perspectives.
It means different things from
the perspective of practice,
of enlightenment or stories.
Therefore you need to
continue studying it.
If you listen to Dharma talks
and continue studying,
it'll take 6 months to a year
for your skepticism to fade away.
What you've known as Buddhism may not
all be what the Buddha actually taught.
You'll have moments when you realize
what certain principles actually meant.
And in other moments,
things you thought
you already knew will
come back to confuse you.
Then there will be things
that are completely different from
what you knew before.
Throughout all of this,
you'll have both happy moments
and confusing moments.
And yet in several months,
you'll find order within
and confusions will be resolved.
You'll understand the context
and meanings behind principles.
These questions will no doubt come up
repeatedly, we'll revisit them later.
In conclusion,
reincarnation and previous lives
are not the core principles of Buddhism.
Then what are the core
beliefs of Buddhism?
It is enlightenment and nirvana.
It is interconnectedness,
the middle path and emptiness.
Previous lives and reincarnation
- these are only side stories.
They are barely leaves of a branch
when we think of Buddhism as a tree.